hi everyone today we are continuing our
implementation of make more our favorite
character level language model
now you'll notice that the background
behind me is different that's because I
am in Kyoto and it is awesome so I'm in
a hotel room here
now over the last few lectures we've
built up to this architecture that is a
multi-layer perceptron character level
language model so we see that it
receives three previous characters and
tries to predict the fourth character in
a sequence using a very simple multi
perceptron using one hidden layer of
neurons with 10ational neuralities
so we'd like to do now in this lecture
is I'd like to complexify this
architecture in particular we would like
to take more characters in a sequence as
an input not just three and in addition
to that we don't just want to feed them
all into a single hidden layer because
that squashes too much information too
quickly instead we would like to make a
deeper model that progressively fuses
this information to make its guess about
the next character in a sequence
and so we'll see that as we make this
architecture more complex we're actually
going to arrive at something that looks
very much like a wavenet
the witness is this paper published by
the point in 2016 and it is also a
language model basically but it tries to
predict audio sequences instead of
character level sequences or Word level
sequences but fundamentally the modeling
setup is identical it is an auto
aggressive model and it tries to predict
next character in a sequence and the
architecture actually takes this
interesting hierarchical sort of
approach to predicting the next
character in a sequence uh with the
street-like structure and this is the
architecture and we're going to
implement it in the course of this video
so let's get started so the starter code
for part five is very similar to where
we ended up in in part three recall that
part four was the manual black
replication exercise that is kind of an
aside so we are coming back to part
three copy pasting chunks out of it and
that is our starter code for part five
I've changed very few things otherwise
so a lot of this should look familiar to
if you've gone through part three so in
particular very briefly we are doing
Imports we are reading our our data set
of words and we are processing their set
of words into individual examples and
none of this data generation code has
changed and basically we have lots and
lots of examples in particular we have
182 000 examples of three characters try
to predict the fourth one and we've
broken up every one of these words into
little problems of given three
characters predict the fourth one so
this is our data set and this is what
we're trying to get the neural lot to do
now in part three we started to develop
our code around these layer modules
um that are for example like class
linear and we're doing this because we
want to think of these modules as
building blocks and like a Lego building
block bricks that we can sort of like
stack up into neural networks and we can
feed data between these layers and stack
them up into a sort of graphs
now we also developed these layers to
have apis and signatures very similar to
those that are found in pytorch so we
have torch.nn and it's got all these
layer building blocks that you would use
in practice and we were developing all
of these to mimic the apis of these so
for example we have linear so there will
also be a torch.nn.linear and its
signature will be very similar to our
signature and the functionality will be
also quite identical as far as I'm aware
so we have the linear layer with the
Bass from 1D layer and the 10h layer
that we developed previously
and linear just as a matrix multiply in
the forward pass of this module batch
number of course is this crazy layer
that we developed in the previous
lecture and what's crazy about it is
well there's many things number one it
has these running mean and variances
that are trained outside of back
propagation they are trained using
exponential moving average inside this
layer when we call the forward pass
in addition to that
there's this training plug because the
behavior of bathroom is different during
train time and evaluation time and so
suddenly we have to be very careful that
bash form is in its correct state that
it's in the evaluation state or training
state so that's something to now keep
track of something that sometimes
introduces bugs
uh because you forget to put it into the
right mode and finally we saw that
Bachelor couples the statistics or the
the activations across the examples in
the batch so normally we thought of the
bat as just an efficiency thing but now
we are coupling the computation across
batch elements and it's done for the
purposes of controlling the automation
statistics as we saw in the previous
video
so it's a very weird layer at least a
lot of bugs
partly for example because you have to
modulate the training in eval phase and
so on
um in addition for example you have to
wait for uh the mean and the variance to
settle and to actually reach a steady
state and so um you have to make sure
that you basically there's state in this
layer and state is harmful uh usually
now I brought out the generator object
previously we had a generator equals g
and so on inside these layers I've
discarded that in favor of just
initializing the torch RNG outside here
use it just once globally just for
Simplicity
and then here we are starting to build
out some of the neural network elements
this should look very familiar we are we
have our embedding table C and then we
have a list of players and uh it's a
linear feeds to Bachelor feeds to 10h
and then a linear output layer and its
weights are scaled down so we are not
confidently wrong at the initialization
we see that this is about 12 000
parameters we're telling pytorch that
the parameters require gradients
the optimization is as far as I'm aware
identical and should look very very
familiar
nothing changed here
uh loss function looks very crazy we
should probably fix this and that's
because 32 batch elements are too few
and so you can get very lucky lucky or
unlucky in any one of these batches and
it creates a very thick loss function
um so we're going to fix that soon
now once we want to evaluate the trained
neural network we need to remember
because of the bathroom layers to set
all the layers to be training equals
false so this only matters for the
bathroom layer so far
and then we evaluate
we see that currently we have validation
loss of 2.10 which is fairly good but
there's still ways to go but even at
2.10 we see that when we sample from the
model we actually get relatively
name-like results that do not exist in a
training set so for example Yvonne kilo
Pros
Alaia Etc so certainly not
reasonable not unreasonable I would say
but not amazing and we can still push
this validation loss even lower and get
much better samples that are even more
name-like
so let's improve this model
okay first let's fix this graph because
it is daggers in my eyes and I just
can't take it anymore
um so last I if you recall is a python
list of floats so for example the first
10 elements
now what we'd like to do basically is we
need to average up
um some of these values to get a more
sort of Representative uh value along
the way so one way to do this is the
following
in part torch if I create for example
a tensor of the first 10 numbers
then this is currently a one-dimensional
array but recall that I can view this
array as two-dimensional so for example
I can use it as a two by five array and
this is a 2d tensor now two by five and
you see what petroch has done is that
the first row of this tensor is the
first five elements and the second row
is the second five elements
I can also view it as a five by two as
an example
and then recall that I can also
use negative one in place of one of
these numbers
and pytorch will calculate what that
number must be in order to make the
number of elements work out so this can
be
this or like that but it will work of
course this would not work
okay so this allows it to spread out
some of the consecutive values into rows
so that's very helpful because what we
can do now is first of all we're going
to create a torshot tensor out of the a
list of floats
and then we're going to view it as
whatever it is but we're going to
stretch it out into rows of 1000
consecutive elements so the shape of
this now becomes 200 by 1000. and each
row is one thousand um consecutive
elements in this list
so that's very helpful because now we
can do a mean along the rows
and the shape of this will just be 200.
and so we've taken basically the mean on
every row so plt.plot of that should be
something nicer
much better
so we see that we basically made a lot
of progress and then here this is the
learning rate Decay so here we see that
the learning rate Decay subtracted a ton
of energy out of the system and allowed
us to settle into sort of the local
minimum in this optimization
so this is a much nicer plot let me come
up and delete the monster and we're
going to be using this going forward now
next up what I'm bothered by is that you
see our forward pass is a little bit
gnarly and takes way too many lines of
code
so in particular we see that we've
organized some of the layers inside the
layers list but not all of them uh for
no reason so in particular we see that
we still have the embedding table a
special case outside of the layers and
in addition to that the viewing
operation here is also outside of our
layers so let's create layers for these
and then we can add those layers to just
our list
so in particular the two things that we
need is here we have this embedding
table and we are indexing at the
integers inside uh the batch XB uh
inside the tensor xB
so that's an embedding table lookup just
done with indexing and then here we see
that we have this view operation which
if you recall from the previous video
Simply rearranges the character
embeddings and stretches them out into a
row and effectively what print that does
is the concatenation operation basically
except it's free because viewing is very
cheap in pytorch no no memory is being
copied we're just re-representing how we
view that tensor so let's create
um
modules for both of these operations the
embedding operation and flattening
operation
so I actually wrote the code in just to
save some time
so we have a module embedding and a
module pattern and both of them simply
do the indexing operation in the forward
pass and the flattening operation here
and this C now will just become a salt
dot weight inside an embedding module
and I'm calling these layers
specifically embedding a platinum
because it turns out that both of them
actually exist in pi torch so in
phytorch we have n and Dot embedding and
it also takes the number of embeddings
and the dimensionality of the bedding
just like we have here but in addition
python takes in a lot of other keyword
arguments that we are not using for our
purposes yet
and for flatten that also exists in
pytorch and it also takes additional
keyword arguments that we are not using
so we have a very simple platform
but both of them exist in pytorch
they're just a bit more simpler and now
that we have these we can simply take
out some of these special cased
um things so instead of C we're just
going to have an embedding
and of a cup size and N embed
and then after the embedding we are
going to flatten
so let's construct those modules and now
I can take out this the
and here I don't have to special case
anymore because now C is the embeddings
weight and it's inside layers
so this should just work
and then here our forward pass
simplifies substantially because we
don't need to do these now outside of
these layer outside and explicitly
they're now inside layers
so we can delete those
but now to to kick things off we want
this little X which in the beginning is
just XB uh the tensor of integers
specifying the identities of these
characters at the input
and so these characters can now directly
feed into the first layer and this
should just work
so let me come here and insert a break
because I just want to make sure that
the first iteration of this runs and
then there's no mistake so that ran
properly and basically we substantially
simplified the forward pass here okay
I'm sorry I changed my microphone so
hopefully the audio is a little bit
better
now one more thing that I would like to
do in order to pytortify our code even
further is that right now we are
maintaining all of our modules in a
naked list of layers and we can also
simplify this uh because we can
introduce the concept of Pi torch
containers so in tors.nn which we are
basically rebuilding from scratch here
there's a concept of containers
and these containers are basically a way
of organizing layers into
lists or dicts and so on so in
particular there's a sequential which
maintains a list of layers and is a
module class in pytorch and it basically
just passes a given input through all
the layers sequentially exactly as we
are doing here
so let's write our own sequential
I've written a code here and basically
the code for sequential is quite
straightforward we pass in a list of
layers which we keep here and then given
any input in a forward pass we just call
all the layers sequentially and return
the result in terms of the parameters
it's just all the parameters of the
child modules
so we can run this and we can again
simplify this substantially because we
don't maintain this naked list of layers
we now have a notion of a model which is
a module and in particular is a
sequential of all these layers
and now parameters are simply just a
model about parameters
and so that list comprehension now lives
here
and then here we are press here we are
doing all the things we used to do
now here the code again simplifies
substantially because we don't have to
do this forwarding here instead of just
call the model on the input data and the
input data here are the integers inside
xB so we can simply do logits which are
the outputs of our model are simply the
model called on xB
and then the cross entropy here takes
the logits and the targets
so this simplifies substantially
and then this looks good so let's just
make sure this runs that looks good
now here we actually have some work to
do still here but I'm going to come back
later for now there's no more layers
there's a model that layers but it's not
a to access attributes of these classes
directly so we'll come back and fix this
later
and then here of course this simplifies
substantially as well because logits are
the model called on x
and then these low Jets come here
so we can evaluate the train and
validation loss which currently is
terrible because we just initialized the
neural net and then we can also sample
from the model and this simplifies
dramatically as well
because we just want to call the model
onto the context and outcome logits
and these logits go into softmax and get
the probabilities Etc so we can sample
from this model
what did I screw up
okay so I fixed the issue and we now get
the result that we expect which is
gibberish because the model is not
trained because we re-initialize it from
scratch
the problem was that when I fixed this
cell to be modeled out layers instead of
just layers I did not actually run the
cell and so our neural net was in a
training mode and what caused the issue
here is the bathroom layer as bathroom
layer of the likes to do because
Bachelor was in a training mode and here
we are passing in an input which is a
batch of just a single example made up
of the context
and so if you are trying to pass in a
single example into a bash Norm that is
in the training mode you're going to end
up estimating the variance using the
input and the variance of a single
number is is not a number because it is
a measure of a spread so for example the
variance of just the single number five
you can see is not a number and so
that's what happened in the master
basically caused an issue and then that
polluted all of the further processing
so all that we have to do was make sure
that this runs and we basically made the
issue of
again we didn't actually see the issue
with the loss we could have evaluated
the loss but we got the wrong result
because basharm was in the training mode
and uh and so we still get a result it's
just the wrong result because it's using
the uh sample statistics of the batch
whereas we want to use the running mean
and running variants inside the bachelor
and so
again an example of introducing a bug
inline because we did not properly
maintain the state of what is training
or not okay so I Rewritten everything
and here's where we are as a reminder we
have the training loss of 2.05 and
validation 2.10
now because these losses are very
similar to each other we have a sense
that we are not overfitting too much on
this task and we can make additional
progress in our performance by scaling
up the size of the neural network and
making everything bigger and deeper
now currently we are using this
architecture here where we are taking in
some number of characters going into a
single hidden layer and then going to
the prediction of the next character
the problem here is we don't have a
naive way of making this bigger in a
productive way we could of course use
our layers sort of building blocks and
materials to introduce additional layers
here and make the network deeper but it
is still the case that we are crushing
all of the characters into a single
layer all the way at the beginning
and even if we make this a bigger layer
and add neurons it's still kind of like
silly to squash all that information so
fast in a single step
so we'd like to do instead is we'd like
our Network to look a lot more like this
in the wavenet case so you see in the
wavenet when we are trying to make the
prediction for the next character in the
sequence it is a function of the
previous characters that are feeding
that feed in but not all of these
different characters are not just
crushed to a single layer and then you
have a sandwich they are crushed slowly
so in particular we take two characters
and we fuse them into sort of like a
diagram representation and we do that
for all these characters consecutively
and then we take the bigrams and we fuse
those into four character level chunks
and then we fuse that again and so we do
that in this like tree-like hierarchical
manner so we fuse the information from
the previous context slowly into the
network as it gets deeper and so this is
the kind of architecture that we want to
implement
now in the wave Nets case this is a
visualization of a stack of dilated
causal convolution layers and this makes
it sound very scary but actually the
idea is very simple and the fact that
it's a dilated causal convolution layer
is really just an implementation detail
to make everything fast we're going to
see that later but for now let's just
keep the basic idea of it which is this
Progressive Fusion so we want to make
the network deeper and at each level we
want to fuse only two consecutive
elements two characters then two bigrams
then two four grams and so on so let's
unplant this okay so first up let me
scroll to where we built the data set
and let's change the block size from 3
to 8. so we're going to be taking eight
characters of context to predict the
ninth character so the data set now
looks like this we have a lot more
context feeding in to predict any next
character in a sequence and these eight
characters are going to be processed in
this tree like structure
now if we scroll here everything here
should just be able to work so we should
be able to redefine the network
you see the number of parameters has
increased by 10 000 and that's because
the block size has grown so this first
linear layer is much much bigger our
linear layer now takes eight characters
into this middle layer so there's a lot
more parameters there but this should
just run let me just break right after
the very first iteration so you see that
this runs just fine it's just that this
network doesn't make too much sense
we're crushing way too much information
way too fast
so let's now come in and see how we
could try to implement the hierarchical
scheme now before we dive into the
detail of the re-implementation here I
was just curious to actually run it and
see where we are in terms of the
Baseline performance of just lazily
scaling up the context length so I'll
let it run we get a nice loss curve and
then evaluating the loss we actually see
quite a bit of improvement just from
increasing the context line length so I
started a little bit of a performance
log here and previously where we were is
we were getting a performance of 2.10 on
the validation loss and now simply
scaling up the contact length from 3 to
8 gives us a performance of 2.02 so
quite a bit of an improvement here and
also when you sample from the model you
see that the names are definitely
improving qualitatively as well
so we could of course spend a lot of
time here tuning
um uh tuning things and making it even
bigger and scaling up the network
further even with the simple
um sort of setup here but let's continue
and let's Implement here model and treat
this as just a rough Baseline
performance but there's a lot of
optimization like left on the table in
terms of some of the hyper parameters
that you're hopefully getting a sense of
now okay so let's scroll up now
and come back up and what I've done here
is I've created a bit of a scratch space
for us to just like look at the forward
pass of the neural net and inspect the
shape of the tensor along the way as the
neural net uh forwards so here I'm just
temporarily for debugging creating a
batch of just say four examples so four
random integers then I'm plucking out
those rows from our training set
and then I'm passing into the model the
input xB
now the shape of XB here because we have
only four examples is four by eight and
this eight is now the current block size
so uh inspecting XP we just see that we
have four examples each one of them is a
row of xB
and we have eight characters here and
this integer tensor just contains the
identities of those characters
so the first layer of our neural net is
the embedding layer so passing XB this
integer tensor through the embedding
layer creates an output that is four by
eight by ten
so our embedding table has for each
character a 10-dimensional vector that
we are trying to learn
and so what the embedding layer does
here is it plucks out the embedding
Vector for each one of these integers
and organizes it all in a four by eight
by ten tensor now
so all of these integers are translated
into 10 dimensional vectors inside this
three-dimensional tensor now
passing that through the flattened layer
as you recall what this does is it views
this tensor as just a 4 by 80 tensor and
what that effectively does is that all
these 10 dimensional embeddings for all
these eight characters just end up being
stretched out into a long row
and that looks kind of like a
concatenation operation basically so by
viewing the tensor differently we now
have a four by eighty and inside this 80
it's all the 10 dimensional uh
vectors just uh concatenate next to each
other
and then the linear layer of course
takes uh 80 and creates 200 channels
just via matrix multiplication
so so far so good now I'd like to show
you something surprising
let's look at the insides of the linear
layer and remind ourselves how it works
the linear layer here in the forward
pass takes the input X multiplies it
with a weight and then optionally adds
bias and the weight here is
two-dimensional as defined here and the
bias is one dimensional here
so effectively in terms of the shapes
involved what's happening inside this
linear layer looks like this right now
and I'm using random numbers here but
I'm just illustrating the shapes and
what happens
basically a 4 by 80 input comes into the
linear layer that's multiplied by this
80 by 200 weight Matrix inside and
there's a plus 200 bias and the shape of
the whole thing that comes out of the
linear layer is four by two hundred as
we see here
now notice here by the way that this
here will create a 4x200 tensor and then
plus 200 there's a broadcasting
happening here about 4 by 200 broadcasts
with 200 uh so everything works here
so now the surprising thing that I'd
like to show you that you may not expect
is that this input here that is being
multiplied uh doesn't actually have to
be two-dimensional this Matrix multiply
operator in pytorch is quite powerful
and in fact you can actually pass in
higher dimensional arrays or tensors and
everything works fine so for example
this could be four by five by eighty and
the result in that case will become four
by five by two hundred
you can add as many dimensions as you
like on the left here
and so effectively what's happening is
that the matrix multiplication only
works on the last Dimension and the
dimensions before it in the input tensor
are left unchanged
so that is basically these um these
dimensions on the left are all treated
as just a batch Dimension so we can have
multiple batch dimensions and then in
parallel over all those Dimensions we
are doing the matrix multiplication on
the last dimension
so this is quite convenient because we
can use that in our Network now
because remember that we have these
eight characters coming in
and we don't want to now uh flatten all
of it out into a large eight-dimensional
vector
because we don't want to Matrix multiply
80.
into a weight Matrix multiply
immediately instead we want to group
these
like this
so every consecutive two elements
one two and three and four and five and
six and seven and eight all of these
should be now
basically flattened out and multiplied
by weight Matrix but all of these four
groups here we'd like to process in
parallel so it's kind of like a batch
Dimension that we can introduce
and then we can in parallel basically
process all of these uh bigram groups in
the four batch dimensions of an
individual example and also over the
actual batch dimension of the you know
four examples in our example here so
let's see how that works effectively
what we want is right now we take a 4 by
and multiply it by 80 by 200
to in the linear layer this is what
happens
but instead what we want is we don't
want 80 characters or 80 numbers to come
in we only want two characters to come
in on the very first layer and those two
characters should be fused
so in other words we just want 20 to
come in right 20 numbers would come in
and here we don't want a 4 by 80 to feed
into the linear layer we actually want
these groups of two to feed in so
instead of four by eighty we want this
to be a 4 by 4 by 20.
so these are the four groups of two and
each one of them is ten dimensional
vector
so what we want is now is we need to
change the flattened layer so it doesn't
output a four by eighty but it outputs a
four by four by Twenty where basically
these um
every two consecutive characters are uh
packed in on the very last Dimension and
then these four is the first batch
Dimension and this four is the second
batch Dimension referring to the four
groups inside every one of these
examples
and then this will just multiply like
this so this is what we want to get to
so we're going to have to change the
linear layer in terms of how many inputs
it expects it shouldn't expect 80 it
should just expect 20 numbers and we
have to change our flattened layer so it
doesn't just fully flatten out this
entire example it needs to create a 4x4
by 20 instead of four by eighty so let's
see how this could be implemented
basically right now we have an input
that is a four by eight by ten that
feeds into the flattened layer and
currently the flattened layer just
stretches it out so if you remember the
implementation of flatten
it takes RX and it just views it as
whatever the batch Dimension is and then
negative one
so effectively what it does right now is
it does e dot view of 4 negative one and
the shape of this of course is 4 by 80.
so that's what currently happens and we
instead want this to be a four by four
by Twenty where these consecutive
ten-dimensional vectors get concatenated
so you know how in Python you can take a
list of range of 10
so we have numbers from zero to nine and
we can index like this to get all the
even parts
and we can also index like starting at
one and going in steps up two to get all
the odd parts
so one way to implement this it would be
as follows we can take e and we can
index into it for all the batch elements
and then just even elements in this
Dimension so at indexes 0 2 4 and 8.
and then all the parts here from this
last dimension
and this gives us the even characters
and then here
this gives us all the odd characters and
basically what we want to do is we make
sure we want to make sure that these get
concatenated in pi torch and then we
want to concatenate these two tensors
along the second dimension
so this and the shape of it would be
four by four by Twenty this is
definitely the result we want we are
explicitly grabbing the even parts and
the odd parts and we're arranging those
four by four by ten right next to each
other and concatenate
so this works but it turns out that what
also works is you can simply use a view
again and just request the right shape
and it just so happens that in this case
those vectors will again end up being
arranged in exactly the way we want so
in particular if we take e and we just
view it as a four by four by Twenty
which is what we want
we can check that this is exactly equal
to but let me call this this is the
explicit concatenation I suppose
um
so explosives dot shape is 4x4 by 20. if
you just view it as 4x4 by 20 you can
check that when you compare to explicit
uh you got a big this is element wise
operation so making sure that all of
them are true that is the truth so
basically long story short we don't need
to make an explicit call to concatenate
Etc we can simply take this input tensor
to flatten and we can just view it in
whatever way we want
and in particular you don't want to
stretch things out with negative one we
want to actually create a
three-dimensional array and depending on
how many vectors that are consecutive we
want to
um fuse like for example two then we can
just simply ask for this Dimension to be
20. and um
use a negative 1 here and python will
figure out how many groups it needs to
pack into this additional batch
dimension
so let's now go into flatten and
implement this okay so I scroll up here
to flatten and what we'd like to do is
we'd like to change it now so let me
create a Constructor and take the number
of elements that are consecutive that we
would like to concatenate now in the
last dimension of the output
so here we're just going to remember
solve.n equals n
and then I want to be careful here
because pipe pytorch actually has a
torch to flatten and its keyword
arguments are different and they kind of
like function differently so R flatten
is going to start to depart from patreon
flatten so let me call it flat flatten
consecutive or something like that just
to make sure that our apis are about
equal
so this uh basically flattens only some
n consecutive elements and puts them
into the last dimension
now here the shape of X is B by T by C
so let me
pop those out into variables and recall
that in our example down below B was 4 T
was 8 and C was 10.
now instead of doing x dot view of B by
negative one
right this is what we had before
we want this to be B by
um negative 1 by
and basically here we want c times n
that's how many consecutive elements we
want
and here instead of negative one I don't
super love the use of negative one
because I like to be very explicit so
that you get error messages when things
don't go according to your expectation
so what do we expect here we expect this
to become t
divide n using integer division here
so that's what I expect to happen
and then one more thing I want to do
here is remember previously all the way
in the beginning n was three and uh
basically we're concatenating
um all the three characters that existed
there
so we basically are concatenated
everything
and so sometimes I can create a spurious
dimension of one here so if it is the
case that x dot shape at one is one then
it's kind of like a spurious dimension
um so we don't want to return a
three-dimensional tensor with a one here
we just want to return a two-dimensional
tensor exactly as we did before
so in this case basically we will just
say x equals x dot squeeze that is a
pytorch function
and squeeze takes a dimension that it
either squeezes out all the dimensions
of a tensor that are one or you can
specify the exact Dimension that you
want to be squeezed and again I like to
be as explicit as possible always so I
expect to squeeze out the First
Dimension only
of this tensor
this three-dimensional tensor and if
this Dimension here is one then I just
want to return B by c times n
and so self dot out will be X and then
we return salt dot out
so that's the candidate implementation
and of course this should be self.n
instead of just n
so let's run
and let's come here now
and take it for a spin so flatten
consecutive
and in the beginning let's just use
eight so this should recover the
previous Behavior so flagging
consecutive of eight uh which is the
current block size
we can do this uh that should recover
the previous Behavior
so we should be able to run the model
and here we can inspect I have a little
code snippet here where I iterate over
all the layers I print the name of this
class and the shape
and so we see the shapes as we expect
them after every single layer in the top
bit so now let's try to restructure it
using our flattened consecutive and do
it hierarchically so in particular
we want to flatten consecutive not just
not block size but just two
and then we want to process this with
linear now then the number of inputs to
this linear will not be an embed times
block size it will now only be n embed
times two
20.
this goes through the first layer and
now we can in principle just copy paste
this
now the next linear layer should expect
and hidden times two
and the last piece of it should expect
and it enters 2 again
so this is sort of like the naive
version of it
um
so running this we now have a much much
bigger model
and we should be able to basically just
forward the model
and now we can inspect uh the numbers in
between
so four byte by 20
was Platinum consecutively into four by
four by Twenty
this was projected into four by four by
two hundred
and then bash storm just worked out of
the box we have to verify that bastron
does the correct thing even though it
takes a three-dimensional impedance that
are two dimensional input
then we have 10h which is element wise
then we crushed it again so if we
flatten consecutively and ended up with
a four by two by 400 now
then linear brought it back down to 200
batch room 10h and lastly we get a 4 by
400 and we see that the flattened
consecutive for the last flatten here uh
it squeezed out that dimension of one so
we only ended up with four by four
hundred and then linear Bachelor on 10h
and uh the last linear layer to get our
logents and so The Lodges end up in the
same shape as they were before but now
we actually have a nice three layer
neural nut and it basically corresponds
to whoops sorry it basically corresponds
exactly to this network now except only
this piece here because we only have
three layers whereas here in this
example there's uh four layers with the
total receptive field size of 16
characters instead of just eight
characters so the block size here is 16.
so this piece of it's basically
implemented here
um now we just have to kind of figure
out some good Channel numbers to use
here now in particular I changed the
number of hidden units to be 68 in this
architecture because when I use 68 the
number of parameters comes out to be 22
000 so that's exactly the same that we
had before and we have the same amount
of capacity at this neural net in terms
of the number of parameters but the
question is whether we are utilizing
those parameters in a more efficient
architecture so what I did then is I got
rid of a lot of the debugging cells here
and I rerun the optimization and
scrolling down to the result we see that
we get the identical performance roughly
so our validation loss now is 2.029 and
previously it was 2.027 so controlling
for the number of parameters changing
from the flat to hierarchical is not
giving us anything yet
that said there are two things
um to point out number one we didn't
really torture the um architecture here
very much this is just my first guess
and there's a bunch of hyper parameters
search that we could do in order in
terms of how we allocate uh our budget
of parameters to what layers number two
we still may have a bug inside the
bachelor 1D layer so let's take a look
at
um uh that because it runs but does it
do the right thing
so I pulled up the layer inspector sort
of that we have here and printed out the
shape along the way and currently it
looks like the batch form is receiving
an input that is 32 by 4 by 68 right and
here on the right I have the current
implementation of Bachelor that we have
right now
now this bachelor assumed in the way we
wrote it and at the time that X is
two-dimensional so it was n by D where n
was the batch size so that's why we only
reduced uh the mean and the variance
over the zeroth dimension but now X will
basically become three-dimensional so
what's happening inside the bachelor
right now and how come it's working at
all and not giving any errors the reason
for that is basically because everything
broadcasts properly but the bachelor is
not doing what we need what we wanted to
do
so in particular let's basically think
through what's happening inside the
bathroom uh looking at what's what's do
What's Happening Here
I have the code here
so we're receiving an input of 32 by 4
by 68 and then we are doing uh here x
dot mean here I have e instead of X but
we're doing the mean over zero and
that's actually giving us 1 by 4 by 68.
so we're doing the mean only over the
very first Dimension and it's giving us
a mean and a variance that still
maintain this Dimension here
so these means are only taking over 32
numbers in the First Dimension and then
when we perform this everything
broadcasts correctly still
but basically what ends up happening is
when we also look at the running mean
the shape of it so I'm looking at the
model that layers at three which is the
first bathroom layer and they're looking
at whatever the running mean became and
its shape
the shape of this running mean now is 1
by 4 by 68.
right instead of it being
um you know just a size of dimension
because we have 68 channels we expect to
have 68 means and variances that we're
maintaining but actually we have an
array of 4 by 68 and so basically what
this is telling us is this bash Norm is
only
this bachelor is currently working in
parallel
over
4 times 68 instead of just 68 channels
so basically we are maintaining
statistics for every one of these four
positions individually and independently
and instead what we want to do is we
want to treat this four as a batch
Dimension just like the zeroth dimension
so as far as the bachelor is concerned
it doesn't want to average we don't want
to average over 32 numbers we want to
now average over 32 times four numbers
for every single one of these 68
channels
and uh so let me now
remove this
it turns out that when you look at the
documentation of torch.mean
so let's go to torch.me
in one of its signatures when we specify
the dimension
we see that the dimension here is not
just it can be in or it can also be a
tuple of ins so we can reduce over
multiple integers at the same time over
multiple Dimensions at the same time so
instead of just reducing over zero we
can pass in a tuple 0 1.
and here zero one as well and then
what's going to happen is the output of
course is going to be the same
but now what's going to happen is
because we reduce over 0 and 1 if we
look at immin.shape
we see that now we've reduced we took
the mean over both the zeroth and the
First Dimension
so we're just getting 68 numbers and a
bunch of spurious Dimensions here
so now this becomes 1 by 1 by 68 and the
running mean and the running variance
analogously will become one by one by
68. so even though there are the
spurious Dimensions uh the current the
current the correct thing will happen in
that we are only maintaining means and
variances for 64 sorry for 68 channels
and we're not calculating the mean
variance across 32 times 4 dimensions so
that's exactly what we want and let's
change the implementation of bash term
1D that we have so that it can take in
two-dimensional or three-dimensional
inputs and perform accordingly so at the
end of the day the fix is relatively
straightforward basically the dimension
we want to reduce over is either 0 or
the Tuple zero and one depending on the
dimensionality of X so if x dot and dim
is two so it's a two dimensional tensor
then Dimension we want to reduce over is
just the integer zero
L if x dot ending is three so it's a
three-dimensional tensor then the dims
we're going to assume are zero and one
that we want to reduce over and then
here we just pass in dim
and if the dimensionality of X is
anything else we'll now get an error
which is good
um so that should be the fix now I want
to point out one more thing we're
actually departing from the API of Pi
torch here a little bit because when you
come to batch room 1D and pytorch you
can scroll down and you can see that the
input to this layer can either be n by C
where n is the batch size and C is the
number of features or channels or it
actually does accept three-dimensional
inputs but it expects it to be n by C by
L
where LSA like the sequence length or
something like that
so um
this is problem because you see how C is
nested here in the middle and so when it
gets three-dimensional inputs this bash
term layer will reduce over zero and two
instead of zero and one so it basically
Pi torch batch number one D layer
assumes that c will always be the First
Dimension whereas we'll we assume here
that c is the last Dimension and there
are some number of batch Dimensions
beforehand
um
and so
it expects n by C or M by C by all we
expect and by C or n by L by C
and so it's a deviation
um
I think it's okay I prefer it this way
honestly so this is the way that we will
keep it for our purposes
so I redefined the layers re-initialize
the neural net and did a single forward
pass with a break just for one step
looking at the shapes along the way
they're of course identical all the
shapes are the same but the way we see
that things are actually working as we
want them to now is that when we look at
the bathroom layer the running mean
shape is now one by one by 68. so we're
only maintaining 68 means for every one
of our channels and we're treating both
the zeroth and the First Dimension as a
batch Dimension which is exactly what we
want so let me retrain the neural lot
now okay so I retrained the neural net
with the bug fix we get a nice curve and
when we look at the validation
performance we do actually see a slight
Improvement so we went from 2.029 to
2.022 so basically the bug inside the
bathroom was holding up us back like a
little bit it looks like and we are
getting a tiny Improvement now but it's
not clear if this is statistical
significant
um
and the reason we slightly expect an
improvement is because we're not
maintaining so many different means and
variances that are only estimated using
using 32 numbers effectively now we are
estimating them using 32 times 4 numbers
so you just have a lot more numbers that
go into any one estimate of the mean and
variance and it allows things to be a
bit more stable and less Wiggly inside
those estimates of those statistics so
pretty nice with this more General
architecture in place we are now set up
to push the performance further by
increasing the size of the network so
for example I bumped up the number of
embeddings to 24 instead of 10 and also
increased number of hidden units but
using the exact same architecture we now
have 76 000 parameters and the training
takes a lot longer but we do get a nice
curve and then when you actually
evaluate the performance we are now
getting validation performance of 1.993
so we've crossed over the 2.0 sort of
territory and right about 1.99 but we
are starting to have to wait quite a bit
longer and we're a little bit in the
dark with respect to the correct setting
of the hyper parameters here and the
learning rates and so on because the
experiments are starting to take longer
to train and so we are missing sort of
like an experimental harness on which we
could run a number of experiments and
really tune this architecture very well
so I'd like to conclude now with a few
notes we basically improved our
performance from a starting of 2.1 down
to 1.9 but I don't want that to be the
focus because honestly we're kind of in
the dark we have no experimental harness
we're just guessing and checking and
this whole thing is terrible we're just
looking at the training loss normally
you want to look at both the training
and the validation loss together and the
whole thing looks different if you're
actually trying to squeeze out numbers
that said we did implement this
architecture from the wavenet paper but
we did not implement this specific uh
forward pass of it where you have a more
complicated a linear layer sort of that
is this gated linear layer kind of and
there's residual connections and Skip
connections and so on so we did not
Implement that we just implemented this
structure I would like to briefly hint
or preview how what we've done here
relates to convolutional neural networks
as used in the wavenet paper and
basically the use of convolutions is
strictly for efficiency it doesn't
actually change the model we've
implemented
so here for example
let me look at a specific name to work
with an example so there's a name in our
training set and it's DeAndre and it has
seven letters so that is eight
independent examples in our model so all
these rows here are independent examples
of the Android
now you can forward of course any one of
these rows independently so I can take
my model and call call it on any
individual index notice by the way here
I'm being a little bit tricky
the reason for this is that extra at
seven that shape is just
um one dimensional array of eight so you
can't actually call the model on it
you're going to get an error because
there's no batch dimension
so when you do extra at
a list of seven then the shape of this
becomes one by eight so I get an extra
batch dimension of one and then we can
forward the model
so
that forwards a single example and you
might imagine that you actually may want
to forward all of these eight
um at the same time
so pre-allocating some memory and then
doing a for Loop eight times and
forwarding all of those eight here will
give us all the logits in all these
different cases
now for us with the model as we've
implemented it right now this is eight
independent calls to our model
but what convolutions allow you to do is
it allow you to basically slide this
model efficiently over the input
sequence and so this for Loop can be
done not outside in Python but inside of
kernels in Cuda and so this for Loop
gets hidden into the convolution
so the convolution basically you can
cover this it's a for Loop applying a
little linear filter over space of some
input sequence and in our case the space
we're interested in is one dimensional
and we're interested in sliding these
filters over the input data
so this diagram actually is fairly good
as well
basically what we've done is here they
are highlighting in Black one individ
one single sort of like tree of this
calculation so just calculating the
single output example here
um
and so this is basically what we've
implemented here we've implemented a
single this black structure we've
implemented that and calculated a single
output like a single example
but what collusions allow you to do is
it allows you to take this black
structure and kind of like slide it over
the input sequence here and calculate
all of these orange outputs at the same
time or here that corresponds to
calculating all of these outputs of
um at all the positions of DeAndre at
the same time
and the reason that this is much more
efficient is because number one as I
mentioned the for Loop is inside the
Cuda kernels in the sliding so that
makes it efficient but number two notice
the variable reuse here for example if
we look at this circle this node here
this node here is the right child of
this node but is also the left child of
the node here
and so basically this node and its value
is used twice
and so right now in this naive way we'd
have to recalculate it but here we are
allowed to reuse it
so in the convolutional neural network
you think of these linear layers that we
have up above as filters and we take
these filters and they're linear filters
and you slide them over input sequence
and we calculate the first layer and
then the second layer and then the third
layer and then the output layer of the
sandwich and it's all done very
efficiently using these convolutions
so we're going to cover that in a future
video the second thing I hope you took
away from this video is you've seen me
basically Implement all of these layer
Lego building blocks or module building
blocks and I'm implementing them over
here and we've implemented a number of
layers together and we've also
implemented these these containers and
we've overall pytorchified our code
quite a bit more
now basically what we're doing here is
we're re-implementing torch.nn which is
the neural networks library on top of
torch.tensor and it looks very much like
this except it is much better because
because it's in pi torch instead of
jingling my Jupiter notebook so I think
going forward I will probably have
considered us having unlocked
um torch.nn we understand roughly what's
in there how these modules work how
they're nested and what they're doing on
top of torture tensor so hopefully we'll
just uh we'll just switch over and
continue and start using torch.net
directly the next thing I hope you got a
bit of a sense of is what the
development process of building deep
neural networks looks like which I think
was relatively representative to some
extent so number one we are spending a
lot of time in the documentation page of
pytorch and we're reading through all
the layers looking at documentations
where the shapes of the inputs what can
they be what does the layer do and so on
unfortunately I have to say the
patreon's documentation is not are very
good they spend a ton of time on
Hardcore engineering of all kinds of
distributed Primitives Etc but as far as
I can tell no one is maintaining any
documentation it will lie to you it will
be wrong it will be incomplete it will
be unclear so unfortunately it is what
it is and you just kind of do your best
um with what they've given us
um number two
uh the other thing that I hope you got a
sense of is there's a ton of trying to
make the shapes work and there's a lot
of gymnastics around these
multi-dimensional arrays and are they
two-dimensional three-dimensional
four-dimensional uh what layers take
what shapes is it NCL or NLC and you're
promoting and viewing and it just can
get pretty messy and so that brings me
to number three I very often prototype
these layers and implementations in
jupyter notebooks and make sure that all
the shapes work out and I'm spending a
lot of time basically babysitting the
shapes and making sure everything is
correct and then once I'm satisfied with
the functionality in the Jupiter
notebook I will take that code and copy
paste it into my repository of actual
code that I'm training with and so then
I'm working with vs code on the side so
I usually have jupyter notebook and vs
code I develop in Jupiter notebook I
paste into vs code and then I kick off
experiments from from the reaper of
course from the code repository so
that's roughly some notes on the
development process of working with
neurons lastly I think this lecture
unlocks a lot of potential further
lectures because number one we have to
convert our neural network to actually
use these dilated causal convolutional
layers so implementing the comnet number
two potentially starting to get into
what this means whatever residual
connections and Skip connections and why
are they useful
number three we as I mentioned we don't
have any experimental harness so right
now I'm just guessing checking
everything this is not representative of
typical deep learning workflows you have
to set up your evaluation harness you
can kick off experiments you have lots
of arguments that your script can take
you're you're kicking off a lot of
experimentation you're looking at a lot
of plots of training and validation
losses and you're looking at what is
working and what is not working and
you're working on this like population
level and you're doing all these hyper
parameter searches and so we've done
none of that so far so how to set that
up and how to make it good I think as a
whole another topic number three we
should probably cover recurring neural
networks RNs lstm's grooves and of
course Transformers so many uh places to
go and we'll cover that in the future
for now bye sorry I forgot to say that
if you are interested I think it is kind
of interesting to try to beat this
number 1.993 because I really haven't
tried a lot of experimentation here and
there's quite a bit of fruit potentially
to still purchase further so I haven't
tried any other ways of allocating these
channels in this neural net maybe the
number of dimensions for the embedding
is all wrong maybe it's possible to
actually take the original network with
just one hidden layer and make it big
enough and actually beat my fancy
hierarchical Network it's not obvious
that would be kind of embarrassing if
this did not do better even once you
torture it a little bit maybe you can
read the weight net paper and try to
figure out how some of these layers work
and Implement them yourselves using what
we have
and of course you can always tune some
of the initialization or some of the
optimization and see if you can improve
it that way so I'd be curious if people
can come up with some ways to beat this
and yeah that's it for now bye